Finding Aid for the J. Paul Getty Family Collected Papers, circa 1880s-1989, undated IA20009
Institutional Records and Archives
- J. Paul Getty papers, 1909-1977; 1982-1984,; 1989,; undated; (bulk 1912-1976); Series I.; 17.6 Linear Feet (22 boxes, 1 flat file)
  - Art collecting and collections, 1934-1974; 1977,; 1982,; undated; (bulk 1934-1974); Series I.A.; 2.4 Linear Feet (10 boxes)
    - Art collections correspondence, 1934-1959; 1970-1972
      - Schaeffer Galleries, 1939 (Box 1986.IA.48-04, Folder 21)
      - F. Schnitterjer and Son, 1937 (Box 1986.IA.48-04, Folder 22)
      - Security First National Bank vault 1, 1942-1943; undated (Box 1986.IA.48-04, Folder 23)
      - Arnold Seligmann, Rey and Co., Inc., 1939; (2 folders) (Box 1986.IA.48-04, Folder 24-25)
      - Sorolla paintings, 1934; 1942 (Box 1986.IA.48-04, Folder 26)
      - Sotheby and Co., 1938-1940 (Box 1986.IA.48-04, Folder 27)
      - Spink and Son, Ltd., 1949-1953; (2 folders) (Box 1986.IA.48-04, Folder 28-29)
      - Stendahl Gallery, 1934; 1939 (Box 1986.IA.48-05, Folder 2)
      - T-V miscellaneous, 1939-1952; undated (Box 1986.IA.48-05, Folder 3)
      - Tessier's Ltd., 1939 (Box 1986.IA.48-05, Folder 4)
      - Thierard Frères, 1937 (Box 1986.IA.48-05, Folder 5)
      - Duc De Trévise, Paris, 1938-1939; undated (Box 1986.IA.48-05, Folder 6)
      - Vardi, New York, 1937 (Box 1986.IA.48-05, Folder 7)
      - Arthur S. Vernay, 1948-1949 (Box 1986.IA.48-05, Folder 8)
      - W-Z miscellaneous, 1938-1950 (Box 1986.IA.48-05, Folder 9)
      - Michael Williams, Ltd., 1938-1939; undated (Box 1986.IA.48-05, Folder 10)
      - Woog Meyer, Paris, 1938-1939 (Box 1986.IA.48-05, Folder 11)
    - Inventories, curators' notes, and insurance policies, 1938-1974; 1977,; 1982,; undated
      Materials are arranged in chronological order.
      - Consular invoices, oceanic shipments, declaration of free entry, Port de France, Volendam, Champlain, 1938; (3 folders) (Box 1986.IA.48-05, Folder 18-20)
      - Curators' notes: typed excerpts from J. Paul Getty's diaries related to art, selected by Museum curators after Getty's death, 1938-1974; (2 folders) (Box 1986.IA.22-01, Folder 17-18)
      - "History of Antique and Fine Art Purchases,", 1939 (Box 1986.IA.48-05, Folder 17)
      - Consular invoices, oceanic shipments, declaration of free entry, SS Pacific Grove, SS Excambion, SS Wisconsin, SS Northern Prince, 1940; (3 folders) (Box 1986.IA.48-05, Folder 21-23)
      - French and Co. Inc. storage inventory, 1941 (Box 1986.IA.48-05, Folder 24)
      - "J. Paul Getty Art Objects and Antiques as of August 31, 1942" and related correspondence, (3 folders) (Box 1986.IA.48-05, Folder 25-26)
      - Inventory, 1942 (Box 1986.IA.48-05, Folder 27)
      - Inventories, 1942; 1946,; 1948-1950,; undated (Box 1986.IA.48-05, Folder 28)
      - Inventory, 1951 (Box 1986.IA.48-05, Folder 29)
      - Inventory compiled by Charles Packer, 1952 (Box 1986.IA.48-06, Folder 1)
      - Insurance policies on art objects, 1954-1958 (Box 1986.IA.48-10, Folder 1)
      - Sutton Place inventory, 1964; (5 folders) (Box 1986.IA.48-15, Folder 2-6)
      - Inventory of tapestries at Sutton Place, 1982; undated (Box 1986.IA.22-01, Folder 3)
      - Inventories, undated (Box 1986.IA.48-06, Folder 4)
      - Inventory of books, undated; (3 folders) (Box 1986.IA.48-06, Folder 2-3)
      - Silver inventory, undated (Box 1986.IA.48-06, Folder 5)
  - Business and personal papers, 1909-1914; 1920-1977,; undated; Series I.B.; 6.5 Linear Feet (12 boxes)
    Material is arranged by format: correspondence, financial records, legal records, and other papers.
    Material comprises some of the personal papers and business records maintained by art collector and oil tycoon J. Paul Getty, gathered from a variety of sources. Material dates from 1909 to 1977 and includes personal correspondence, financial records, and legal documents.
    The correspondence primarily consists of letters received by J. Paul Getty ("Paul") dating from 1912-1914 and 1926-1977. The early correspondence is the most personal; it reflects the relationship between Paul and his parents and hints at the relationships between Paul and two of his wives, Helen "Ann" Rork and Louise Dudley "Teddy" Lynch. A small selection of letters were sent from Getty to an acquaintance, Ann Mitchell. The correspondence from "friends and acquaintances" varies in content and degree of intimacy. Correspondence from "others" primarily contains letters from persons not acquainted with Mr. Getty and contains letters about various business ventures and interests, requests for information, fan mail, and letters of acknowledgment from Getty's staff in response to the incoming mail. Some of the correspondence to Mr. Getty from others post-dates his death.
    The financial records consist of a promissory note, correspondence, financial statements, annual reports, a will, and tax statements relating to J. Paul Getty and the J. Paul Getty estate, dating 1909, 1926, 1928, 1932 to 1942, 1950 to 1957, 1976 to 1977, and undated. The records primarily describe the financial well-being of Getty family businesses as well as Getty's estate at the time of his death. The earliest document (1909) is a hand-written note signed by seventeen-year-old Paul to his father, George F. Getty I, acknowledging the partial receipt of his allowance ($2.60). Some of the early tax and financial documents postdate George F. Getty's death, but concern his various companies. Other records detail the status of J. Paul Getty's estate and his personal financial status through tax returns and financial statements.
    The legal documents describe legal and financial relationships within the Getty family through correspondence, wills, and other legal documents, dating from 1926 to 1976. The materials include an unsigned carbon copy of an early J. Paul Getty will (dated May 1, 1950) and a copy of Sarah C. Getty's will. Some of the records concern Getty's wives and children, including prenuptial agreements, divorce decrees, financial settlements, alimony discussions, child support negotiations, and an inventory of possessions. These records concern Getty's second wife, Allene Ashby; his third wife, Adolphine "Fini" Helmle; his fourth wife, Helen "Ann" Rork; and his fifth wife, Louise Dudley "Teddy" Lynch.
    The other papers comprise various dissociated papers of J. Paul Getty, dating from 1920 to 1952 and undated. The papers include samples of his early schoolwork; receipts for auto purchases; vital records and meeting minutes from some of his oil companies; notes regarding diet and health; and scattered diary entries. Please note that the Institutional Archives, Getty Research Institute holds Mr. Getty's more complete diaries: J. Paul Getty Diaries (1938-1946, 1948-1976), Finding aid no. IA40009.
    - Correspondence, 1912-1914; 1926-1977,; undated
      Material is arranged according to correspondent, beginning with immediate family and moving outward by levels of intimacy, finally to fan mail and others not actually acquainted with Mr. Getty.
      Note
      For additional correspondence to J. Paul Getty from his wives, see Legal records in this series (I.B.). For letters written from J. Paul Getty to his parents, see Series II.A. George F. Getty I papers. Family history and correspondence and Series II.B. Sarah C. Getty papers.
      - From father, George F. Getty, 1913-1914; 1920,; 1926,; 1928,; undated (Box 2010.IA.17-01)
      - Telegram and letter from father George F. Getty, 1912; 1926 (Box 2019.IA.56-01)
      - From mother, Sarah C. Getty, 1926; 1930,; 1936,; 1938,; undated (Box 2010.IA.17-01)
      - From wife, Helen "Ann" Rork, 1931; 1941; (bulk 1931) (Box 2010.IA.17-01)
      - From wife, Louise Dudley "Teddy" Lynch, 1954; 1955,; undated (Box 2010.IA.17-01)
      - From friends and acquaintances, 1912; 1913,; 1926-1949 (scattered),; undated; (2 folders) (Box 2010.IA.17-01)
      - Letters from J. Paul Getty to Ann Mitchell, 1934-1936 (Box Shared 2014.IA.02; 2018.IA.58)
        Includes five letters. Four are authored by J. Paul Getty; one is uncertain.
      - From others, 1946-1977; (4 folders) (Box 1986.IA.48-05, Folder 12-13)
      - Outgoing: letter of introduction and copy of one letter, 1926; 1941 (Box 2010.IA.17-01)
      - Medical, 1965-1966 (Box 1986.IA.48-05, Folder 16)
        Access Restrictions
        RESTRICTED. This material is closed until 2066.
    - Financial records, 1909; 1926-1942,; 1950-1957,; 1976-1977,; undated; (bulk 1932-1957)
      Material is arranged in rough chronological order.
      - Acknowledgment of allowance received from father and promissory note from J. Paul Getty to father, 1909; 1928 (Box 2010.IA.17-01)
      - Check register, Mexico, 1926 (Box 2010.IA.17-01)
      - Cancelled check, loan agreement, and expense notes, 1929; 1932,; undated (Box 2010.IA.17-01)
      - Document regarding 1932 tax filing related to Minnehoma Oil, signed "Paul Getty,", 1933 (Box 2010.IA.17-04)
      - George F. Getty, Inc. financial information, 1936 (Box 1986.IA.48-06, Folder 23)
      - George F. Getty, Inc. 1936 tax returns, 1938 deficient tax letter (Box 1986.IA.48-06, Folder 22)
      - George F. Getty, Inc. IRS audit letter and report, 1938 (Box 1986.IA.48-06, Folder 24)
      - Getty family personal and corporate annual reports, 1938; (1 volume) (Box 1986.IA.48-07)
        One bound volume, prepared for J. Paul Getty, comprising financial reports for the year 1938 on the following persons and corporations: George F. Getty, Inc.; Ada Oil Corporation; Santa Fe Company; Getty Realty Corporation; J. Paul Getty, Trustee "under that certain declaration of Trust dated December 31, 1934, wherein Sarah C. Getty is the trustor and J. Paul Getty, trustee"; J. Paul Getty; and Sarah C. Getty.
      - Income tax history of Sarah C. Getty, February 4, 1941 (Box 2010.IA.17-01)
      - J. Paul Getty signed affidavit and claim related to personal income taxes, 1941; 1942 (Box 2010.IA.17-01)
      - J. Paul Getty signed affidavit related to personal income taxes, August 17, 1942 (Box 2010.IA.17-01)
      - Correspondence re: 1950 taxes, 1950-1954 (Box 1986.IA.48-07, Folder 2)
      - Correspondence re: 1951 tax return, 1951-1954 (Box 1986.IA.48-07, Folder 3)
      - Balance sheets, notes, re: 1951 taxes, 1951-1952 (Box 1986.IA.48-07, Folder 4)
      - J. Paul Getty tax returns, 1952; (3 folders) (Box 1986.IA.48-07, Folder 5-7)
      - Balance sheets, notes, re: 1952 tax return (Box 1986.IA.48-07, Folder 8)
      - J. Paul Getty financial statements, 1952; 1953 (Box 1986.IA.48-07, Folder 1)
      - Correspondence re: 1952 JPG tax return, 1953-1955; 1957; (2 folders) (Box 1986.IA.48-08, Folder 1-2)
      - Income tax returns, JPG, 1953; (2 folders) (Box 1986.IA.48-08, Folder 3-4)
      - Pacific Western Oil Corporation and subsidiary companies financial statement, as of December 31, 1955, March 9, 1956 (Box 1986.IA.48-15, Folder 7)
      - Check stubs and spending notes, 1957 (Box 1986.IA.22-01, Folder 19)
      - "Residuary Trust of Sarah C. Getty financial statement as of March 31, 1976 and 1975,", April 20, 1976 (Box 1986.IA.48-15, Folder 8)
      - J. Paul Getty estate tax return, table of contents, schedules A-P, and will, circa 1976; (8 folders) (Box 1986.IA.48-08, Folder 5-12)
      - J. Paul Getty estate financial statements from Ticor Trust Department Title Insurance and Trust, October 1976; (2 folders) (Box 1986.IA.48-08, Folder 14-15)
      - J. Paul Getty estate inheritance tax declaration, 1977 (Box 1986.IA.48-08, Folder 13)
    - Legal records, 1926-1976
      Material is arranged in rough chronological order, beginning with agreements made between Mr. Getty and his wives.
      - Agreements with wives:
        Mr. Getty was married and divorced five times. The records herein concern the following persons, often refering to them by their maiden names or their married names (when they remarried after divorcing Mr. Getty):
        Second wife: Allene Ashby
        Third wife: Adolphine "Fini" Helmle, mother of Jean Ronald Getty
        Fourth wife: Helen "Ann" Rork (also known as Helen Ann Rork Wilson and Helen Ann Rork Light), mother of Eugene Paul and Gordon Peter Getty
        Fifth wife: Louise Dudley Lynch (also known as Theodora Lynch, Teddy Lynch, and Teddy Getty Gaston), mother of Timothy Ware Getty
        - Allene Ashby: prenuptial agreement (incomplete) and signed divorce settlement agreement, 1926; 1928 (Box 2010.IA.17-01)
        - Adolphine "Fini" Helmle: prenuptial agreement, correspondence, divorce settlement agreement, 1932; 1935,; 1948 (Box 2010.IA.17-01)
        - Helen "Ann" Rork:
          - Divorce complaint and transcript, 1936 (Box 1986.IA.48-06, Folder 8)
          - Correspondence and miscellaneous, 1936; 1938-1939 (Box 1986.IA.48-06, Folder 9)
          - Correspondence, 1941-1975; (4 folders) (Box 1986.IA.48-06, Folder 10-13)
          - Alimony agreement, October 1, 1935 (Box 1986.IA.48-06, Folder 14)
          - Supplemental agreement, December 23, 1938 (Box 1986.IA.48-06, Folder 15)
          - Letter to Ann Getty from JPG acknowledging receipt of all indebtedness, December 23, 1938 (Box 1986.IA.48-06, Folder 16)
          - Legal documents, correspondence re: alimony, child support, Ann Light Trust, 1938-1976 (Box 1986.IA.48-06, Folder 17)
        - Louise Dudley "Teddy" Lynch: inventories of possessions, 1950 (Box 1986.IA.48-06, Folder 20)
      - Sarah C. Getty will (copy), 1942 (Box 1986.IA.48-06, Folder 6)
      - Sarah C. Getty Trust: cross-complaint, April 9, 1948 (Box 1986.IA.48-06, Folder 7)
      - Life insurance policies for Eugene Paul (Jean Paul, Jr.) and Gordon Peter Getty, 1936; undated (Box 2010.IA.17-04)
        RESTRICTED. This material is closed for the life of Gordon Peter Getty.
      - Schedules of collateral required at Citizens National Trust and Savings Bank for Gordon Peter Getty, Ann Rork Wilson, and Eugene Paul Getty, undated (Box 1986.IA.48-06, Folder 18)
      - Schedule of endowment policies for Eugene Paul Getty and Gordon Peter Getty, undated (Box 1986.IA.48-06, Folder 19)
      - Letter and certificate of occupancy for construction of art gallery at the Getty Ranch House, 1945; 1949 (Box 1986.IA.48-06, Folder 21)
      - J. Paul Getty Last Will and Testament (carbon copy), May 1, 1950 (Box 2010.IA.17-01)
    - Other papers, 1918-1952; undated
      Material is arranged alphabetically by topic.
      - Auto purchases, 1927; 1942,; undated (Box 2010.IA.17-01)
      - Diary entries and notes:
        The diary entries herein are scant and dissociated from J. Paul Getty's more complete diaries, which are held by the Institutional Archives, Getty Research Institute: J. Paul Getty Diaries (1938-1946, 1948-1976), Finding aid no. IA40009.
        - Diary entries, April 22, 1936; August 1940 (Box 2010.IA.17-01)
        - Diary of Texas/Mexico trip, May 29-July 18, 1948 (Box 2010.IA.17-01)
        - Typed transcript of diary entries, March 18-April 13, 1949; December 15-17, 1950 (Box 2010.IA.17-01)
        - Notes regarding diet and health, undated (Box 2010.IA.17-01)
      - Oil business:
        Materials are arranged alphabetically by name of corporation.
        - Carl B. King Drilling Co. drilling agreement with J. Paul Getty, 1937 (Box 2010.IA.17-01)
        - Getty Oil Company/Oklahoma Oil Corporation minutes and other records, 1920-1952; (1 loose-leaf binder) (Box 2010.IA.17-05)
        - Oklahoma Oil stock certificates (cancelled), 1922 (Box 2010.IA.17-01)
        - Pacific Western Oil Corporation correspondence and reports, 1936; 1937,; 1948,; 1950,; 1951 (Box 2010.IA.17-01)
        - San Joaquin Oil Company articles of incorporation, meeting minutes, and balance sheets, 1930-1934; (1 folder and 1 scrapbook) (Box 2010.IA.17-05)
          Documents in folder were found loose inside front cover of scrapbook.
        - Unidentified oil company, handwritten notes/ suggestions, undated (Box 2010.IA.17-01)
      - Plan (sketch) for Getty tomb, undated (Box 1986.IA.48-09, Folder 10)
      - Private investigation of Helen "Ann" Rork Getty "Office Memo,", September 7, 1935 (Box 2010.IA.17-02)
      - Schoolwork: Exposition of stanza from Gray's "Elegy Written in a Country Churchyard,", undated (Box 1986.IA.22-01, Folder 16)
      - Schoolwork: Grammar 7A composition book with one entry in it, undated (Box 2010.IA.17-02)
      - Travel documents: Permit to enter Mexico (1932); applications for permits to enter occupied territories in Europe (1948, 1949); and undated note to self regarding application procedures (Box 2010.IA.17-02)
      - United States Army application for commission, signed and notarized, November 4, 1918 (Box 2010.IA.17-02)
  - Publications, typescripts, and related material, 1940-1976; 1989,; undated; (bulk 1940-1967); Series I.C.; 1.4 Linear Feet (6 boxes)
    Material is arranged according to format, beginning with correspondence, followed by Mr. Getty's published works, typescripts, and drafts.
    Records consist of correspondence, invoices, manuscripts, books, and articles, dating from 1940 to 1989 and undated, by or about J. Paul Getty. The bulk of the correspondence concerns Collector's choice, co-authored by Getty and Ethel Le Vane. This correspondence was sent to and received by Le Vane and is mostly concerned with the foreign language editions of the book. The manuscripts/typescripts include drafts of Europe in the eighteenth century, a complete copy of J. Paul Getty as collector, a sample chapter of Midas: the life of J. Paul Getty, by Alice Goldfarb Marquis; and copies of Collector's choice in three languages.
    - Correspondence, 1940-1975
      - Printing: history and catalogue, 1940-1941; (3 folders) (Box 1986.IA.48-09, Folder 1-3)
      - Correspondence re: Collector's choice, 1955-1964; 1970,; 1975; (5 folders) (Box 1986.IA.48-09, Folder 4-8)
      - J. Paul Getty correspondence with Playboy/HMH Publishing Co. staff and Hugh Hefner, fan mail, and internal memos primarily re: How to Be Rich, and articles contributed by Getty, 1961; 1966,; 1967 (Box Shared 2014.IA.02; 2018.IA.58)
    - Publications, 1949; 1955-1968,; 1976,; 1989,; undated; (bulk 1955-1968)
      - Published works:
        - Getty, J. Paul, Europe in the eighteenth century, 1949 (Box 1987.IA.05-01)
        - Getty, J. Paul, and Ethel Le Vane, Streifzüge eines kunstsammlers, 1955 (Box 1987.IA.05-01)
        - Getty, J. Paul, and Ethel Le Vane, Vingt mille lieues dans les musées, 1955 (Box 1987.IA.05-01)
        - Getty, J. Paul, and Ethel Le Vane, Collector's choice, 1956 (Box 1987.IA.05-01)
        - Hewins, Ralph, J. Paul Getty: The richest American, 1961 (Box 1987.IA.05-01)
        - Getty, J. Paul, "What makes an executive?" Playboy Magazine, May 1962 (Box 1987.IA.05-01)
        - Getty, J. Paul, My life and fortunes, 1963 (Box 1987.IA.05-01)
        - Getty, J. Paul, How to be rich, 1965 (Box 1987.IA.05-01)
        - Getty, J. Paul, The joys of collecting, 1965 (Box 1987.IA.05-01)
        - Getty, J. Paul, "The homogenized man: a plea for the preservation of the individual in our increasingly pigeonholed society," Playboy Magazine, August 1965 (Box 1987.IA.05-01)
        - Getty, J. Paul, "Quitting time," Playboy Magazine (photocopy), February 1967 (Box 1987.IA.05-01)
        - Getty, J. Paul, The golden age, 1968 (Box 1987.IA.05-01)
        - Getty, J. Paul, As I see it: the autobiography of J. Paul Getty, 1976 (Box 1987.IA.05-01)
        - Biographies in bronze: portrait sculpture by Robert Berks, exhibition catalog featuring a bronze bust of J. Paul Getty, 1989 (Box 1987.IA.05-01)
      - Typescripts and drafts:
        - "J. Paul Getty as a collector," articles by Museum curators, Fredericksen, Wilson, and Frel, 1982; (8 folders) (Box 1986.IA.22-01, Folder 4-11)
        - Sample chapter, Marquis, "Midas: The life of J. Paul Getty,", 1983; (2 folders) (Box 1986.IA.22-01, Folder 14-15)
        - Europe in the eighteenth century typescript and annotated drafts, undated (Box 2010.IA.17-02)
        - Getty, J. Paul, "A journey from Corinth,", undated; (2 folders) (Box Shared 1987.IA.16-01; 2004.IA.17; 2009.IA.36; 2011.IA.44; 2022.IA.88)
  - Ephemera and clippings, 1914-1920; 1932-1954,; 1974,; 1982-1984,; undated; Series I.D.; 7.3 Linear Feet (7 boxes, 1 flat file)
    Material is arranged first by format and then alphabetically.
    Material comprises ephemera and clippings collected by or pertaining to J. Paul Getty. Items date from 1939 to 1989 and undated, and include some of J. Paul Getty's foreign driving licenses; an audio recording of an interview with Mr. Getty; an article from a Minneapolis historical society concerning Getty's childhood with photographs and documents from that institution; every-day artwork; and other ephemera and clippings.
    - Ephemera:
      - Audio recording of interview with J. Paul Getty (Rome), 1952; (1 DVD) (Box 1986.IA.22-01, Folder 1)
      - Caricature of J. Paul Getty by Jack Rosen, undated (Box Shared 1987.IA.16-01; 2004.IA.17; 2009.IA.36; 2011.IA.44; 2022.IA.88)
      - Cruise passenger list and brochure, 1914; 1920 (Box 1986.IA.22-01, Folder 24)
      - Driving licenses and auto club cards, 1933; 1939 (Box 2010.IA.17-02)
      - Event programs, unattributed poem, loose envelopes, 1912; 1932,; 1933,; 1935 (Box 2010.IA.17-02)
      - Oil painting by the artist Jack L. Gray, depicting the oil tanker George F. Getty at sea, undated (Object 1998.IA.06)
      - Poster from Occidental College (Los Angeles) soliciting funds, circa 1942 (Box 2010.IA.17-04)
      - [Portrait of a Woman], drawing by Gerald Leslie Brockhurst, 1916 (Flatfile 1986.IA.40)
      - Valise adorned with travel stickers, undated; (1 leather valise, approximately 18 x 15 x 12 inches) (Box 1997.IA.08-01)
    - Clippings:
      - Spartan Aircraft Company clippings and letter, 1942-1947; 1974 (Box 1986.IA.22-01, Folder 23)
      - "New Getty Museum houses sculpture" clipping, 1954 (Box 1986.IA.48-09, Folder 9)
      - "Getty writes about money and women" clipping from San Jose Mercury News clipping, November 21, 1976 (Box 2010.IA.17-04)
      - J. Paul Getty in Minneapolis articles and supplemental material, 1982-1984 (Box 1986.IA.22-01, Folder 22)
- George F. Getty I and Sarah C. Getty papers, 1890; 1904-1921,; 1928,; 1931-1934,; 1939,; undated; (bulk 1911-1912); Series II.; 1 Linear Feet (6 boxes)
  Material is arranged into two series:
  Series II.A. George F. Getty I papers, 1890, 1904-1921, 1928, undated (bulk 1911-1912)
  Series II.B Sarah C. Getty papers, 1908, 1909, 1919, 1921, 1931-1934, 1939, undated.
  Biographical Note
  George Franklin Getty I (1855-1930) and Sarah Catherine McPherson Risher Getty (1852-1941) were the parents of billionaire Jean Paul Getty, whom they called "Paul." Sarah and George met at Michigan University and were married in 1879. They used Sarah's dowry of one hundred dollars to pay off George's college debt, enabling him to leave his teaching job at a grammar school to study law.
  George graduated from Michigan University's Law Department in 1882 and passed the bar exam shortly thereafter. He became a successful attorney and insurance executive in Minneapolis, Minnesota. In 1890 a typhoid epidemic struck the Getty family, severely weakening Sarah and claiming their daughter, Gertrude Lois Getty (age ten). Although George and Sarah felt the loss of Gertrude for the rest of their lives, they were overjoyed with the birth of their son, Paul, in 1892.